South of U Street Oral History Project OHP025
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
South of U Street Oral History Project
2012
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
District of Columbia. Public Library
OHP025
137 Gigabytes 57 MOV and DOC file masters transferred to archive by Shaw librarians Eric Riley and Casey Danielson. Original External HD to be returned to Danielson. Files were transferred on the oral history project laptop. Files were backed up onto the external hard drive containing digitized oral histories (DIG_00009).
Content Description
Digital audio recordings and PDF transcripts of 10 oral history interviews recorded by Shaw Library staff to document the Shaw neighborhood and the effect of the 1968 riots on its community.
Oral History; Assassination; Riots; Urban renewal; Segregation; Gentrification; Audio; Digital materials
- Series 1: Transcripts, 10 Files
  - Jacqueline Rogers Hart interview transcript, 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-01.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Biographical / Historical
    Jacqueline ''Jackie'' Rogers Hart was born in Washington D.C. and lived in D.C. and Atlantic City until the age of twelve. She began attending the Fashion Institution of Technology in New York at the age of 17, but eventually moved back to D.C. to work as a secretary.
    Scope and Contents
    Transcript of oral history interviews with Jacqueline Rogers Hart. She discusses her memories of the 1968 riots, which occurred while she was working as a secretary at a law firm. Hart also gives her perspective on how Shaw has changed over time, both in terms of its cost of living and the fact that is not is as close knit as it used to be.
  - Kenneth Tolliver interview transcript, 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-06.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Kenneth Tolliver was born in Washington D.C. He briefly lived in North Carolina.
    Transcript of oral history interviews oral history interviews with Kenneth Tolliver. A native of D.C., he discusses his experience of the 1968 riots, which he describes as a "battle scene in a movie." He reflects on the consequences of the riots in the community, noting that many of the businesses that were destroyed never returned. Tolliver sees gentrification as an issue that Shaw has been dealing with since the riots. Tolliver also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Barbara Taylor Hunter interview transcript, 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-11.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Born in Richmond, Virginia, Barbara Taylor Hunter moved to Washington, D.C. to attend Howard University where she majored in Art and Design and Fashion Design. After graduating Howard, she attended the Fashion Institute in New York and subsequently moved back to D.C. to teach in D.C..
    Transcript of oral history interviews with Barbara Taylor Hunter. Taylor describes the fashion and culture of Shaw and Howard University in the 1960s. She touches upon the nature of Howard's political organizations and the area's music scene. Hunter reflects on how Shaw changed as a result of the 1968 riots. She notes that much of the neighborhood's older character was lost from destruction of architecture, the departure of many families, and an increase in housing costs. As a former high school teacher, she also discusses the schools in Shaw and her continued relationships with former students.
  - Elizabeth Williams Frazier interview transcript, 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-15.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Born in Rock Hill, South Carolina, Elizabeth Williams Frazier moved to Washington, D.C. as a child.
    Transcript of oral history interviews with Elizabeth Williams Frazier. Frazier moved to Shaw in 1963 as a child and later attended Shaw Junior High School. Her first experience on U Street was going to see a movie when she was 18 years old. Frazier also mentions Fide's House, which she describes as a place where people in the community could go for food and clothing. She remembers Shaw as a close knit community where everybody knew each other. Her telling of the riots begins with hearing that Martin Luther King Jr. had been assassinated. She describes how much of the neighborhood was destroyed and states that it remained in that state for a number of years. Frazier also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Karen Keegan-Isard interview transcript, 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-19.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Karen Keegan-Isard, moved to Washington D.C. in the 1970s with her husband. The couple later moved to Shaw and established a community bank.
  - Yvonne Baskerville interview transcript, 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-24.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 1941, Yvonne Baskerville later moved to Washington D.C. with her family.
  - Mill Butler interview transcript, 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-28.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Mill Butler was born in Washington D.C. in 1954.
    General
    The second of the two video oral history interviews with Mill Butler was lost some time after its creation. The contents of that video can be found in the interview transcript document.
    Transcript of oral history interviews with Mill Butler. In his interviews Butler describes where he went for entertainment, including the Howard Theater and Republic Theater. Butler also details how car dealerships left the community after the 1968 riots due to their inability to be insured.
  - Alexander Padro interview transcript, 2012-06; dcpl_ohp25-30.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Alexander Padro is a community organizer and the executive director of Shaw Main Streets.
    Transcript of oral history interviews with Alexander Padro. A long-time Shaw community organizer and leader, Padro describes his involvement within the neighborhood's developments. He reflects on Shaw's history, particularly on the reasons for the 1968 riots and the effects it had on the community. He describes how urban renewal shaped Shaw after the riots, with churches and large scale housing projects leading the development of the community instead of businesses. He briefly touches on the disagreement within community groups, such as the Model Inner Cities Community Organization and the Land Redevelopment Agency, about urban renewal. Padro also speaks briefly about the crack epidemic.
  - Betty May Brooks-Cole interview transcript, 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-35.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Betty May Brooks-Cole was born in Washington D.C.
    Transcript of oral history interviews with Betty May Brooks-Cole. In her interviews, she describes the entertainment venues for African Americans on U Street, including the Howard Theater and the Republic Theater and notes some of the musical acts that she saw perform, which included Chuck Brown and the Four Tops. She also speaks about the segregation of department stores. Brooks-Cole describes as well her fright at being on 7th street in the middle of the 1968 riots and how she felt in the aftermath of the riots.
  - Ibrahim Mumin interview transcript, 2012-06; dcpl_ohp25-43.tra.pdf; 1 Files
    Born in Columbus, Georgia, Mumin attended Howard University where he was a student activist. At the time of the interview, he was executive director of Shaw Project Area Committee, a Washington, D.C. nonprofit organization which focuses on the development Shaw area.
    Transcript of oral history interviews with Ibrahim Mumin. In his interviews, Mumin describes his activism during his time as a student at Howard, which attempted to push Howard to become more involved with the community. Mumin explains a sense of activism attached him to Shaw. He mentions Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw community. He also touches upon the entertainment venues and restaurants he used to visit in the area. Mumin notes how his experience in activism and the confrontations it led to prepared him for the 1968 riots. Reflecting on why the riots occurred, Mumin felt that people struck out at businesses out of anger, which led to many businesses and middle-class whites fleeing the community altogether. Mumin also presents his perspective on Shaw's present and future, in terms of economics, culture, and community.
- Series 2: Interviews
  - Jacqueline Rogers Hart interview (part 1 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-01.mov; 1 Files
    The first of four oral history interviews with Jacqueline Rogers Hart. She discusses her memories of the 1968 riots, which occurred while she was working as a secretary at a law firm. Hart also gives her perspective on how Shaw has changed over time, both in terms of its cost of living and the fact that is not is as close knit as it used to be.
  - Jacqueline Rogers Hart interview (part 2 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-02.mov; 1 Files
    The second of four oral history interviews with Jacqueline Rogers Hart. She discusses her memories of the 1968 riots, which occurred while she was working as a secretary at a law firm. Hart also gives her perspective on how Shaw has changed over time, both in terms of its cost of living and the fact that is not is as close knit as it used to be.
  - Jacqueline Rogers Hart interview (part 3 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-03.mov; 1 Files
    The third of four oral history interviews with Jacqueline Rogers Hart. She discusses her memories of the 1968 riots, which occurred while she was working as a secretary at a law firm. Hart also gives her perspective on how Shaw has changed over time, both in terms of its cost of living and the fact that is not is as close knit as it used to be.
  - Jacqueline Rogers Hart interview (part 4 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-04.mov; 1 Files
    The fourth of four oral history interviews with Jacqueline Rogers Hart. She discusses her memories of the 1968 riots, which occurred while she was working as a secretary at a law firm. Hart also gives her perspective on how Shaw has changed over time, both in terms of its cost of living and the fact that is not is as close knit as it used to be.
  - Kenneth Tolliver interview (part 1 of 5), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-06.mov; 1 Files
    Kenneth Tolliver was born in Washington D.C.. He briefly lived in North Carolina.
    The first of five oral history interviews with Kenneth Tolliver. A native of D.C., he discusses his experience of the 1968 riots, which he describes as like a ''battle scene in a movie.'' He reflects on the consequences of the riots in the community, noting that many of the businesses that were destroyed never returned. Tolliver sees gentrification as an issue that Shaw has been dealing with since the riots. Tolliver also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Kenneth Tolliver interview (part 2 of 5), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-07.mov; 1 Files
    The second of five oral history interviews with Kenneth Tolliver. A native of D.C., he discusses his experience of the 1968 riots, which he describes as like a ''battle scene in a movie.'' He reflects on the consequences of the riots in the community, noting that many of the businesses that were destroyed never returned. Tolliver sees gentrification as an issue that Shaw has been dealing with since the riots. Tolliver also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Kenneth Tolliver interview (part 3 of 5), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-08.mov; 1 Files
    The third of five oral history interviews with Kenneth Tolliver. A native of D.C., he discusses his experience of the 1968 riots, which he describes as like a ''battle scene in a movie.'' He reflects on the consequences of the riots in the community, noting that many of the businesses that were destroyed never returned. Tolliver sees gentrification as an issue that Shaw has been dealing with since the riots. Tolliver also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Kenneth Tolliver interview (part 4 of 5), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-09.mov; 1 Files
    The four of five oral history interviews with Kenneth Tolliver. A native of D.C., he discusses his experience of the 1968 riots, which he describes as like a ''battle scene in a movie.'' He reflects on the consequences of the riots in the community, noting that many of the businesses that were destroyed never returned. Tolliver sees gentrification as an issue that Shaw has been dealing with since the riots. Tolliver also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Kenneth Tolliver interview (part 5 of 5), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-10.mov; 1 Files
    The fifth of five oral history interviews with Kenneth Tolliver. A native of D.C., he discusses his experience of the 1968 riots, which he describes as like a ''battle scene in a movie.'' He reflects on the consequences of the riots in the community, noting that many of the businesses that were destroyed never returned. Tolliver sees gentrification as an issue that Shaw has been dealing with since the riots. Tolliver also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Barbara Taylor Hunter interview (part 1 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-11.mov; 1 Files
    The first of four oral history interviews with Barbara Taylor Hunter. Taylor describes the fashion and culture of Shaw and Howard University in the 1960s. She touches upon the nature of Howard's political organizations and the area's music scene. Hunter reflects on how Shaw changed as a result of the 1968 riots. She notes that much of the neighborhood's older character was lost from destruction of architecture, the departure of many families, and an increase in housing costs. As a former high school teacher, she also discusses the schools in Shaw and her continued relationships with former students.
  - Barbara Taylor Hunter interview (part 2 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-12.mov; 1 Files
    The second of four oral history interviews with Barbara Taylor Hunter. Taylor describes the fashion and culture of Shaw and Howard University in the 1960s. She touches upon the nature of Howard's political organizations and the area's music scene. Hunter reflects on how Shaw changed as a result of the 1968 riots. She notes that much of the neighborhood's older character was lost from destruction of architecture, the departure of many families, and an increase in housing costs. As a former high school teacher, she also discusses the schools in Shaw and her continued relationships with former students.
  - Barbara Taylor Hunter interview (part 3 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-13.mov; 1 Files
    The third of four oral history interviews with Barbara Taylor Hunter. Taylor describes the fashion and culture of Shaw and Howard University in the 1960s. She touches upon the nature of Howard's political organizations and the area's music scene. Hunter reflects on how Shaw changed as a result of the 1968 riots. She notes that much of the neighborhood's older character was lost from destruction of architecture, the departure of many families, and an increase in housing costs. As a former high school teacher, she also discusses the schools in Shaw and her continued relationships with former students.
  - Barbara Taylor Hunter interview (part 4 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-14.mov; 1 Files
    The fourth of four oral history interviews with Barbara Taylor Hunter. Taylor describes the fashion and culture of Shaw and Howard University in the 1960s. She touches upon the nature of Howard's political organizations and the area's music scene. Hunter reflects on how Shaw changed as a result of the 1968 riots. She notes that much of the neighborhood's older character was lost from destruction of architecture, the departure of many families, and an increase in housing costs. As a former high school teacher, she also discusses the schools in Shaw and her continued relationships with former students.
  - Elizabeth Williams Frazier interview (part 1 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-15.mov; 1 Files
    The first of four oral history interviews with Elizabeth Williams Frazier. Frazier moved to Shaw in 1963 as a child and later attended Shaw Junior High School. Her first experience on U Street was going to see a movie when she was 18 years old. Frazier also mentions Fide's House, which she describes as a place where people in the community could go for food and clothing. She remembers Shaw as a close knit community where everybody knew each other. Her telling of the riots begins with hearing that Martin Luther King Jr. had been assassinated. She describes how much of the neighborhood was destroyed and states that it remained in that state for a number of years. Frazier also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Elizabeth Williams Frazier interview (part 2 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-16.mov; 1 Files
    The second of four oral history interviews with Elizabeth Williams Frazier. Frazier moved to Shaw in 1963 as a child and later attended Shaw Junior High School. Her first experience on U Street was going to see a movie when she was 18 years old. Frazier also mentions Fide's House, which she describes as a place where people in the community could go for food and clothing. She remembers Shaw as a close knit community where everybody knew each other. Her telling of the riots begins with hearing that Martin Luther King Jr. had been assassinated. She describes how much of the neighborhood was destroyed and states that it remained in that state for a number of years. Frazier also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Elizabeth Williams Frazier interview (part 3 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-17.mov; 1 Files
    The third of four oral history interviews with Elizabeth Williams Frazier. Frazier moved to Shaw in 1963 as a child and later attended Shaw Junior High School. Her first experience on U Street was going to see a movie when she was 18 years old. Frazier also mentions Fide's House, which she describes as a place where people in the community could go for food and clothing. She remembers Shaw as a close knit community where everybody knew each other. Her telling of the riots begins with hearing that Martin Luther King Jr. had been assassinated. She describes how much of the neighborhood was destroyed and states that it remained in that state for a number of years. Frazier also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Elizabeth Williams Frazier interview (part 4 of 4), 2012-04; dcpl_ohp25-18.mov; 1 Files
    The fourth of four oral history interviews with Elizabeth Williams Frazier. Frazier moved to Shaw in 1963 as a child and later attended Shaw Junior High School. Her first experience on U Street was going to see a movie when she was 18 years old. Frazier also mentions Fide's House, which she describes as a place where people in the community could go for food and clothing. She remembers Shaw as a close knit community where everybody knew each other. Her telling of the riots begins with hearing that Martin Luther King Jr. had been assassinated. She describes how much of the neighborhood was destroyed and states that it remained in that state for a number of years. Frazier also discusses Fides House, a community center that offered services to the Shaw neighborhood.
  - Karen Keegan-Isard interview (part 1 of 5), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-19.mov; 1 Files
    The first of five oral history interviews with Karen Keegan-Isard. In her interviews she describes how she first relocated to Washington D.C. with her husband and eventually moved to Shaw. In the interview, Keegan-Isard speaks about the community bank her husband established in Shaw. She also speaks about her experience of the 1968 riots.
  - Karen Keegan-Isard interview (part 2 of 5), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-20.mov; 1 Files
    The second of five oral history interviews with Karen Keegan-Isard. In her interviews she describes how she first relocated to Washington D.C. with her husband and eventually moved to Shaw. In the interview, Keegan-Isard speaks about the community bank her husband established in Shaw. She also speaks about her experience of the 1968 riots.
  - Karen Keegan-Isard interview (part 3 of 5), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-21.mov; 1 Files
    The third of five oral history interviews with Karen Keegan-Isard. In her interviews she describes how she first relocated to Washington D.C. with her husband and eventually moved to Shaw. In the interview, Keegan-Isard speaks about the community bank her husband established in Shaw. She also speaks about her experience of the 1968 riots.
  - Karen Keegan-Isard interview (part 4 of 5), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-22.mov; 1 Files
    The fourth of five oral history interviews with Karen Keegan-Isard. In her interviews she describes how she first relocated to Washington D.C. with her husband and eventually moved to Shaw. In the interview, Keegan-Isard speaks about the community bank her husband established in Shaw. She also speaks about her experience of the 1968 riots.
  - Karen Keegan-Isard interview (part 5 of 5), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-23.mov; 1 Files
    The fifth of five oral history interviews with Karen Keegan-Isard. In her interviews she describes how she first relocated to Washington D.C. with her husband and eventually moved to Shaw. In the interview, Keegan-Isard speaks about the community bank her husband established in Shaw. She also speaks about her experience of the 1968 riots.
  - Yvonne Baskerville interview (part 1 of 4), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-24.mov; 1 Files
    The first of four oral history interviews with Yvonne Baskerville. In her interviews Yvonne Baskerville discusses her early education as an African American, detailing her experience as a student at Dunbar High School, a segregated black high school. Baskerville also describes her sense of shock in hearing the news of Martin Luther King Jr.'s assassination. She also details her encounter with the D.C.'s rodent population.
  - Yvonne Baskerville interview (part 2 of 4), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-25.mov; 1 Files
    The second of four oral history interviews with Yvonne Baskerville. In her interviews Yvonne Baskerville discusses her early education as an African American, detailing her experience as a student at Dunbar High School, a segregated black high school. Baskerville also describes her sense of shock in hearing the news of Martin Luther King Jr.'s assassination. She also details her encounter with the D.C.'s rodent population.
  - Yvonne Baskerville interview (part 3 of 4), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-26.mov; 1 Files
    The third of four oral history interviews with Yvonne Baskerville. In her interviews Yvonne Baskerville discusses her early education as an African American, detailing her experience as a student at Dunbar High School, a segregated black high school. Baskerville also describes her sense of shock in hearing the news of Martin Luther King Jr.'s assassination. She also details her encounter with the D.C.'s rodent population.
  - Yvonne Baskerville interview (part 4 of 4), 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-27.mov; 1 Files
    The fourth of four oral history interviews with Yvonne Baskerville. In her interviews Yvonne Baskerville discusses her early education as an African American, detailing her experience as a student at Dunbar High School, a segregated black high school. Baskerville also describes her sense of shock in hearing the news of Martin Luther King Jr.'s assassination. She also details her encounter with the D.C.'s rodent population.
  - Mill Butler interview, 2012, 2012-05; dcpl_ohp25-28.mov; 1 Files
  - Alexander Padro interview (part 1 of 5), 2012-06; dcpl_ohp25-30.mov; 1 Files